Hi, I'm michael lewis number program manager on...team.
this is a pre-recorded session for build and I'll be talking about navigation commanding,
for example,
so, since you'll be watching this online I want to give you brief overview some stuff that I'll be talking about so you have a
good idea of what you'll be getting over the next forty five minutes to an
hour what you want to skip ahead come back later watch it over again or just go lot
watch smother sessions and then later come back to this one so I'll start by talking about navigation
briefly touch on some patterns and what controls we have that will
help if you want implement some of those patterns be talking about commanding as well and,
really understanding the changes of happened commanding area will look at some of the history of how
...evolved and where we are now with windows...and
look at what's new and if you have an existing app and you're going
to upgrade it what you should consider or if you're building a new app and there's just some things you need to understand the
about the controls for commanding navigation patterns to start there's
no required pattern you can you can really use whatever pattern
fits best for your app we're not we're not telling you have to do one thing or the other
we we've looked at some of the patterns that we
...platform and other platforms to try and make sure that if there's an experience that you
need to provide that you can do that so some of the common patterns that we do
R pivot pattern if you're familiar with windows phone you see this on a number of
apps like the mail app where you have these individual pivots and you can swipe through
room move between the different pivot items
there's tabs where images have a bar with some buttons and you can tap on the barn quickly
jumped to an area of your app there's the hub and spoke where it's nice
big landing page area and you can quickly move between different areas of your app.
There's master detail ...you like the mail out,
for example, if...folders and you can click on one of those you can see the details
for that item and then we've got hamburger which is one that you may not have
seen a lot on windows but
it's prevalent on a number of other platforms and this is
a pattern that if it's the right experience for your app you can use it and we're going to
talk briefly about how you might build that on windows and so.
Some of the controls are useful if you wanted to build some of these experiences
are these navigation experiences are the hub control
the pivot the app...and split view which is new so how
...previously converged on both windows phone and windows and we've updated
it's still present you can use it for your app pivot was previously only available on the phone.
And, now it's there on windows as well so you can you can use a pivot and...experience
that spans from the large-screen from small-screen the large-screen app...was really only
their on windows and...often used at the top as a navigation menu
...still there you can continue...it we've made available on the phone as well.
Split use new control that...talk about more detail.
Split view is this control has really to content areas you can see the
...on the left and the content...on the right...that's we think of
as a building-block it's not just for navigation so it's not even
...into the navigation framework it's a building-block you can use
to create and navigation experience but you don't have to user for navigation if there's other places where you
feel that split use a control that will help you provide experience your app
...provide you can use this but you control.
So, as a basic...building-block we don't have this built-in button the might see
on another frameworks this hamburger button there is an icon you can use so if you
...want to provide this experience and you don't want to create your own icon
you-can use this icon from the...amd ltwo assets font.
one-click...this...this is a new font that are asses seems provided it's a great...all these icons
...been designed...on the m square which makes it easier use these as an asset
your app so in the past if you're familiar with the citgo ui symbol font
you there's a bunch of icons you can choose from sometimes are duplicate icons and they
had different sizes and wasn't clear which was the right one in this new font the icons
are easy to pick up a assigned to an area
...say use text blocking give font-size of twenty-four
thirty-two and icons roughly going to fill that space so, it's just
much easier for you...to use...across your app now one
thing you should understand is that this new font the
...to assets font is not a one-to-one mapping with...cigar
...symbol so-if you have a bunch of...places where you're using fontein
icon and you don't specified...family...a symbol
...you just upgrade your app...you may find some of these...using
before aren't there I'll have a note about that later in the slide as well.
Look, at split view here's the api that's really relevant to split view
as control inherits a lot of things but these are the properties that
your most commonly going to want to use.
So, this is a demo of the split
you control where you can see I have the control here with the
...on the left content on the write up above I have a number of controls that are
bounds to the different properties of the split you control so to
...one...understands...right now...the inline mode and what this
...that the pain is affecting the layout so the content is
...fit...that remaining areas on the right side?
Now if I switch the placement of the
...to be on the right side you just see it switch over.
...also set the alpha channel on the background for my pain.
To be something that's semi transparent you can see what...that will have as we switch to some of the other
modes right now there's nothing behind the...so...appears to be opaque if I
close this pane you'll notice that the content resize is
so-if you have some really rich content in here this is not the mode you want to use of
...going to be turning opening and closing it regularly because it's going to cause your
content to be a laid out over and over again which could affect the perf of your
app so let's switch to one of the other
modes compact inline this is very similar the inline mode
the difference being that you now have this compact area that you can put some ui
...a bit of a hint to the user and also
...can interact with while it's still in the closed state.
If it opens you'll see again it pushes that content over.
Overlay mode you now see that it it's just sizes says
it's an overlay the pain is over top of the content when it's open as
a opens and closes it does not affect layout we have this animation that
plays with it one thing to be aware of in this mode as well as it does have some light
dismiss behavior so if I tap out or click outside of the...it closes.
Compact overlay is very similar
to compact inline of course being overlay it's still going to
overlay the rest of the content so it does affect layout by that compact amount but when it
opens and closes you can see it just goes over top of the content.
Again, you can switch the
sides you can change the size of that pain
when it opens so let's make it something bigger you can see it to
...right over when singly compact size phi one that compact
hint be larger?
I could set that and, have it start from
...from a larger hand?
And, then open to be the full width.
So, we talk about how you might uses control if you're trying to build
a hamburger type experience is if you think you should consider so
one is the structure of how you want to set up your app I'm going to show you what I've done
in a demo app and one of the things that you should see you'll notice is that I have
this top-level app...it's really just a page the reviews
and on the content of the page I have the split you control within the content of the split view
I've place the frame and then it's in there that I'm navigating between different pages.
...I have app shows a page a provides nice design-time experience
it's also it takes into account the visible bounds so it...the content so,
for example, if I want to run this exact same app on the phone you'll know that on
the phone that there's a system trade has the clock...other things that
appears the top and by default that would go over your app and
if you by using a page it takes that into
...pushes it down so there's no visual collision there for the menu items on my hamburger
...I've style radio buttons I could have chosen...subclass am
...styling works it's nice because they have a check state so as you
select one of those items that's one that shows up is the user knows that's the area
...in of your app.
And, then you can see thatI've put frame as the content for the split view and
noticing considers where you put the hamburger button itself you'll see what I've done
in my absolutely switch over and show you that now.
So, here we have the app and you can
see how I've set up and start off and we have the app shell.
That really taking a place of the frame.
The app shell has a frame within it that employing out and hooking up to the different events
for navigation failed as well as when I call the navigate event the sequence here
is very similar to what you get with the basic app when you
start load it by default from visual studio.
Now if we look at the app running.
Okay, here we can see the app running and you can see on the left I've got this...
that I set the inline and I've got a number of items that as
a click on them will navigate to different areas of the app.
Here's that same split
...demo again now what I've done is these buttons you can
see these radio buttons so as I check them you can see which one is
selected and where you are in the app if I?
Go on a page go deeper into that area of the page I can drill
...and then I can jump to other areas of the app and I see where I'm at any point I've had my
own back button to the app so that as I'm going back through the stack.
It'll highlight which area I'm in and I've
added these animation so that you get the smooth experience as you transitioning from one area to the other.
As I resize the app itself you'll see what happens I'm going to switch
down to the compact size I can still navigate around.
And, then as I go even further let's assume this was on a phone size screen.
Drops...entirely and I still have just the hamburger button
where I can open the pain and then move quickly between different areas of my app.
Now how this what's happening here in the code.
On the...itself.
Have declared my split view?
Have said a few properties?
And,...above I'm using these adaptive triggers that a different break points
and screen size we'll switch from the properties so you can...setting the root split view
display mode to be compact overlay when the size of the screen is
between...greater than five twenty?
But, less than six hundred forty one as it gets down to the
smaller size between zero and five twenty I'm just switching it to be in the overlay mode.
Within the...itself I have my stack panel radio buttons you can see I've style
these.
So, that they get that look and feel of that's appropriate for this pattern.
And, then here I have the frame on the frame itself I've set of content transition this
...those nice animations
...I'm transition from one for one-page to the next page.
And, I've added this entrance navigation transition info so
is each page comes in it's getting that nice animation that plays.
Now on the very first page.
When I navigate this is my app loading...initially want...animation
we playing so what I've done on the navigate method itself?
Is you can see that I've given it normal pages should go to the arguments
have uses extra parameter to say suppress navigation
transition info on this first-time so in the app first loads there's no animation?
Ok, so, now we're going take a look at commanding will do a bit of a deep dive on
some things of change here in the commanding area.
So, first look at what's happened and where we came from so windows a we
have the app bar and then in a one we introduce the command bar?
And, if you if you go back there was a slide in
the last build conference that you may have seen this where we had
windows eight one we had windows phone aone and what happened was there's a lot of conversions happen
...a lot of the api is that were really the same but...still some things that
...only on one platform or only on the other
and there's some areas where they were conversion had different behaviors
in the area of commanding this is this was true?
What we had was mostly the same api but we had separate binary is and we had some
taylor behavior?
More specifically if we look at the app are the app
are wasn't supported on the phone at all like you couldn't use it if you try to
you get exception runtime on windows the app...was there.
...responding what we call edgy events so someone's
...from the top and bottom of the screen it would appear if
they write clicked or if they use the windows z keyboard shortcut
...the keyboard appear on-screen it also always appear above the keyboard.
And, it was always horizontal so if I had...device and I rotated it
that app or would always appear at the logical bottom or top of the screen?
Now if we look at the command bar which came later and a one.
It was a...parcel lot of the same things on windows...had but it had
a little more structured had...set of primary commands
if you're on the right side and...the secondary commands that appeared on the left side.
Otherwise you see very similar behaviors responded to the edgy gesture
...above the keyboard and it was more
optimized for that experience in windows...on the phone we had
that same api but some different behavior so you can see the primary
commands were this set of commands appear the top.
And, the set of secondary commands appear in this menu that would come up as a
user taped on that dot-dot-dot you see there was no edgy gesture support
...you couldn't...from the top of on the screen causes to appear obviously right click on the
phone wouldn't do anything you couldn't really do it and, the api itself was
wrapping the systems akbar so it wasn't appears
example implementation were surfacing that systems the system app
are up through so you can use in your app and part that was
...the implication was that the page top are was not supports...couldn't use that property
...top of the page on your app and in terms orientation as
you rotate the device rather than always been to logical bottom of the screen the app
...stick to that shortage...always near those hardware buttons for the back
and search in the that go back to the start screen.
Furthermore on the phone had this minimize
mode so being a small-screen if you really want to maximize
the space for the content of your app you could put in this minimize mode and,
just it's still there for the user but not interface
when keyboard appeared if it was in portrait the app are would be
below the keyboard but as you rotate the device again could because
...that side you would...see it appear on the side.
Adjacent to the keyboard.
So, now what
do we have we have one code base one api but we still have this
taylor behavior who we're talking about command bar.
What do I mean by that so to give you a quick look here again we have windows phone
aone the app are experience on the left when
it was opened on the desktop and then what we
...windows ten you'll see a lot of similarities but there's some differences that you should understand?
So, we look at the api.
Here's,
here's that conversion api it was the same between a one-in-ten.
The second of secondary commands.
You'll notice has shifted so before.
These are the secondary commands.
In windows ten they appear here I have to screen shots.
what this is the exact same control the only thing that's different between these two is the
size of the window so...a smaller window size you'll see that menu snaps
be the full width but on a larger screen it
...to the content...contains so the implications
are should be apparent for those of you who have windows aone app you'll see
...was previously the secondary...now move into this menu?
The...is still the same that the command
bar is in a close state and when it's opened it reveals all
of its content which would be both the labels for the primary commands as well as any secondary commands
are now there now what about the app are the app
are you could say is exactly the same as the commander except that it
doesn't have this menu for the app are we're talking about just the bar and the app
...is really an area where you...whatever custom content
you want to the left of this dot-dot-dot now this button itself is
there and present because users need a way interact with this control?
So, if we look at the app...for a moment.
By default windows ten it's going to be visible and minimal size.
In the past it was hidden and someone had to do...gesture to
...to appear or pragmatically you invoke it because that gestures no longer
there for windows ten apps what.
We provide in this minimal...by default and making it easy for your app to move forward
so that the that experience is still very similar users can get to the
commands of your app it also has this dot-dot-dot
button which is basically the replacement for that gesture.
And, one of the things that...still true for the app...is if someone does a right click and it's not
hand-held elsewhere in your app then it'll cause the app rtwo appear.
When you have an app...that's at the top obama screen on a page...pages really the root
of your app so it also affects visual bounds when it
sets through so-if you have a frame in a page using a top-to-bottom app
...what's new for windows ten that was previously there on the phone is
that the content of your page will be pushed up or down slightly
based on the size of that app...when it's in that close state of minimal?
We've also added these api is opening and closing now this
api the close display...I've mention here was previously available only on the phone
is now convergence present for the app are...using
...on windows phone or other devices.
So, we show you a quick demo of the app or we're
going to start by looking at windows aone app ok so here's a
here's a windows ten app that was upgraded from a blank windows
eight app and all it has is top app are and bottom map are and you can see inside
I have basically the same app...I've copied.
With just some controls on the left and right side so that when it runs you get that
experience...may be familiar with on windows ten.
So, here you can see the app.
By default.
I now have this minimal app for both the top-to-bottom in windows
...those...been off the screen entirely.
If I write click you see
they both open but I could also just click on.
Each of these a quick anywhere on the bar or the more buttoned caused
...close sounds talk about the commander.
Member as I said before is really the app are plus more.
Instead of being minimal size by default its compact.
So, you'll see a hand you'll
...the icons for those primary commands but you won't get labels
until you open it doesn't respond to write click this is a change that we've made so,
that the command...gives back the right click for you to
use we encourage you to use other things where it's appropriate, for example, context menu
users familiar with that pattern and you can certainly use in your app.
Memoir we've also given...ability to host custom content so
the passes really...you got the app are button...talk about the
separator and that was pretty much it but now you can put whatever you want inside the command
...I'll show you where that goes member has this menu of commands that's
different than the app are now on...already had this before as before but for
windows that's new and as you saw those commands of move another thing to be a to be aware of is
that the implementations one hundred-percent animal so on phone where we were previously
rapping systems app are now it's alls animal so there may have
been some...issues are things that you ran into and those are all the should all be gone.
Now being one control we still want to give this taylor experience.
And, that's why you'll see...based on the windows size that menu may be
going to the...size or it may be just size into the content.
Another thing to note with the command bars it's no longer limited
...being the top or the bottom of your screen you can now
...inline in your page you'll see what I mean
here we look at one of the apps the people app and on the desktop you can
see they have to command bars they have this one in the
...over here and have one over
the right side and they go down to a mobile device drop down to one
note these do not have to be using the page top-to-bottom
app are properties these could be just placed inline adjacent
other content there's a lot more flexibility jan you should know that
...inline will affect layout but only for that close
size once you tap that more button to open it will not cause...you
...to move around you don't have anything special to get that behaviors just built into the control?
So, if we look at the api.
Here's what's really new for the command...the part this
gray was stuff those converge before.
This is now what we have the close display mode it's present
everywhere you can set one of these nodes...hidden the minimal compact.
And, without an opening and closing property so if you take some action before
it opens then you have a way to hook into that.
We have this member content property is a property
that previously existed but didn't do anything now when
you set content that content will appear to the left
of the primary commands so-if you have no primary commands and you put stuff in the content
...equivalent to the app are you can put whatever you need inside that area.
Now because it supports all...the you can combine them as best needs to the
needs of your app and then...have this overflow presenter style that allows you to get
at this menu here and do some things like change the background color if you need to?
So, let's take a quick look.
At a demo ok so here I have the app that you saw earlier were
to look at the command bar for a moment I have a number of command bars I've placed in
the page here these are all inline.
Now as I mentioned when they open they don't affect
...layout of other control so here I have a button
...itself...a toggle switch they're in a stack panel...
you'll notice that it goes over the button doesn't cause to shift around.
Here the bottom you can still play some align the
top-to-bottom as you see fit having a inline makes it easy for you to move around if you need
to make your app more adaptive and you still get this great experience now
notice that the menu is sizing the content.
If this window size were much smaller sales a phones
...screen than that menu and opens with span the full width and it's more
optimize for someone who's holding the device with their hand they can just touch easily on those different commands.
Now on the app
are itself you can see we've got a toggle button
that appears menu so that's indicated by this with the check mark.
We have flout attached to the buttons if you have more commands you need to share surface
to the user and you can see buttons are
...toggle that's indicated by the...color.
So, if we look at the code here we can see one of the command bars and
...setting the presenter style.
I'm doing style and targeting that command
...overflow presenter and I'm just setting the background to be a like gray.
So, if we go back to the app you can see which one that's this one here now
another thing to note is the behavior of this of this menu
it's going up over everything else when it opens and again it's
...the content so I obviously...in a not a great spot being here on
the left side but if we drop this down so that screen sizes smaller
you'll see that if...space on...switches...to the left edge.
If you need to override some things again like the color maybe the
...you can you can get to that through this camaro overflow presenter.
So, just to recap this is the command...behavior where you notice the layout was only
effected by the size of when the close state the
menu is based on the size the window less than or equal to four hundred and
eighty it...be the full-size the window optimized for
the small-screen devices greater than four-eighty is going to size of the content.
Now if you may not assume this ...the demo but
those commands don't automatically move so as you re sizing the window
those commands will remain but you can programmatic remove them if you need to from
being primary...secondary command and the right visual change will happen for you.
So, when we look at which one...use app are versus the command are?
Use the command bar the app
...we've done work to try and ease the transition for people who have these
legacy apps and you're trying to update them to work well for windows ten.
So, the behaviors there as much as possible
try to keep it the same as it was with some minimal changes we
encourage the switch to the command bar improvise the capabilities the flexibility that I think you'll
need for your app and provides with additional options.
Now when you're upgrading your absolute things you should consider first again recommend you
move to the commander it's not...click automatically so if that's something you're
users will become a custom do then you may need to add that functionality yourself.
When the when the keyboard appears on the screen?
...is not going to a it's not going to move up
with the keyboard unless you have says that page bottom app...property.
Now question to ask is if that's critical for your app do you need to have your commands visible while the
keyboard is...consider scenarios where like on a mobile
device you have it and landscape and the...trying-to type that
keyboards already consuming quite a bit of space and having having those commands
also present how much is that helping the user so,
if you need to you can hide it or just not
show it put in the minimal sizes well other things to be aware of?
The app are...button and app are button has
a different size than it did before they were different between phone
...windows...now converge size.
It's closer to the phone size so if you have an apps localize
and just be aware that may affect where those words are going to wrap you can use a soft...from character in
the string will act as a hint of the indicate where that word should break.
And, if you really need the button to be to be larger we recommend
...use septa min width and not the width and the reason being that if you if you want
to start moving those commands from the primary commands...commands using...what is going to give you the right
behavior using width is not going to give you the experience that you users really want to see.
Now I mention much earlier about this new font...deal to assets phone.
The symbol icon find icon front icon now use
fone by default so if you have for using
fond icon and you didn't set the font family specifically
when you upgrade you may find that there's a number of places where there's no
glare for you get the blank rectangle now simple icon.
Those all those are just moves right forwards so as you upgrade your
app it's going to switch and you're going to get new looking...the icons now those icons themselves
in the buttons they have a smaller space is now twenty by twenty box?
So-if...a path
icon on windows which or phone which assumed to forty by forty you may find that now
your icons getting clipped so one of the things you can do is just take that path
icon and you can assign is the content of the button and
...that interview box and they won't be the same-size...she won't get your icon being clipped.
So, like to thank you for watching help
...formative they'll be some sessions...done live
...build you should definitely go check out there related to some of the concept I've talked about here
geoff arnold and...will be giving a talk talking about the user experience
different models...and controls and
things should consider the to learn more about navigation window ing in windows
...go see this talk...robbers and if you have legacy app and you
...sams...one's going to talk more about that and what it means when you're moving
from whether silverlight or windows aone to the to be a windows
tenure ap and?
Then last of all when you start thinking about building at that's going to scale across all these different screen
sizesthere's newer things you have to think about and tim...her rainier
going to give a talk on that they should definitely go and check out again, thanks for watching
I look forward to getting your feedback in your comments and answering questions you may have.